<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="basics">
    <title>Basic Sage Commands</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>Here you will find a hotch potch of some basic SageMath concepts</p>
    </introduction>

    <section>
        <title>How to define functions</title>

        <sage>
            <input>
                def f(z): return 2*z^3 - z^2 - 7*z + 2
                type(f)
            </input>
            <output>
                &lt;type 'function'&gt;
            </output>
        </sage>

        <sage>
            <input>
                f(2)
            </input>
            <output>
                0
            </output>
        </sage>

        <sage>
            <input>
                plot(f, -2, 3)
            </input>
        </sage>

        <sage>
            <input>
                f(x) = (cos(x)-1)/x^2
                show(f)
            </input>
        </sage>
        <sage>
            <input>
                f(3)
            </input>
            <output>
                1/9*cos(3) - 1/9
            </output>
        </sage>
        <sage>
            <input>
                show(f(pi))
            </input>
            <output>
                -2/pi^2
            </output>
        </sage>
        <sage>
            <input>
                plot(f(x), (-2*pi, 2*pi),ymin = -1, ymax = 1)
            </input>
        </sage>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Symbolic Expressions</title>

        <p>The expand method</p>
        <sage>
            <input>
                z = (x+1)^3
                show(z)
            </input>
            <output>(x+1)^3</output>
        </sage>

        <sage>
            <input>
                z2 = z.expand()
                show(z2)
            </input>
            <output>x^3 + 3*x^2 + 3*x + 1</output>
        </sage>
        <p>Notice how the <code>show()</code> method displays the output in a nicer manner. Without it you will see the
            less pretty output:
            <pre>x^3 + 3*x^2 + 3*x + 1</pre>
        </p>

        <p>Now the reverse! Perform a <code>factor()</code> on the expanded equation.
        </p>
        <sage>
            <input>
                show(z2.factor())
            </input>
            <output>x^3 + 3*x^2 + 3*x + 1</output>
        </sage>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Declaring Variables</title>

        <p>Sage allows us to solve equations not only numerically but <en>symbolically</en>.  To make this possible we have to be able to define variables that are used in the symbollic manipulation.</p>
        <p>We will demonstrate this using a complete differential equation example.</p>

        <subsection>
            <title>Use SageMath to solve differential equations</title>

            <p>Let's learn how to describe and solve differential equations (DEs) with Sage. Unfortunately, as with most
                computer algebra systems, Sage won't allow the user to describe DEs in an intuitive way, and sometimes
                getting a particular result requires nothing less than sneakiness and trickery.
            </p>

            <p>Sage can solve a large class of first-order and second-order Ordinary Differential Equations (ODEs) as
                well as Initial Value Problems (IVPs). This page is meant to show accessible solutions and methods for
                most common kinds of DEs, but it doesn't exhaustively detail all that Sage is capable of.
            </p>

            <p>While using Sage for these examples, remember that unknown named variables must be predeclared — if a
                variable declaration isn't included in an example and you get an error about an undefined variable or an
                error message that has no obvious explanation, be sure to add a declaration for each variable that is
                used, like this:
            </p>
            <sage>
                <input>
                    var('a b c x y z')
                </input>
                <output>(a, b, c, x, y, z)</output>
            </sage>

            <p>For this first example, I'll express the differential equation using common mathematical notation, then
                enter it into Sage using Sage's notation. Here's the mathematical notation for our example:
            </p>

            <men>y(t) + rcy'(t) = 0</men>
            <men>y(0) = 1</men>

            <p>This expression says that the unknown function (the function to be found) produces the sum of y(t) and r
                c y'(t) for any time t, and that the initial value of the function at time zero is 1. (The meaning of r
                and c will become clear after a bit.) This is an example of a differential equation that specifies an
                initial value, as many do. In this case I intend to scale the result after acquiring the result, and
                this initial value makes that easy. Here is how I submit this differential equation to Sage:
            </p>


        </subsection>
        <p>(From
            <url href="http://arachnoid.com/sage/differential1.html#Second_Example">P Lutus - Applying Sage to physics</url>)
        </p>
        <sage>
            <input>
                var('r c t')
                y = function('y')(t)
                de = y + r*c*diff(y,t) == 0
                des = desolve(de,[y,t],[0,1]);des
            </input>
            <output>e^(-t/(c*r))</output>
        </sage>

        <p>Or in the prettier format:</p>
        <sage>
            <input>
                show(des)
            </input>
            <output>e^(-t/(c*r))</output>
        </sage>

        <p>Lets break this entry down:

            <ul>
                <li>
                    <m>var('r c t')</m>
                    tells Sage to predeclare the variables that will be used.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <m>y = function('y')(t)</m>
                    tells Sage that <m>y</m> is a function of <m>t</m>, e.g. as though every time we type <m>y</m> we mean <m>
                    y(t)</m>.
                    This is a way to identify <m>y</m> as a function, not just a variable, and associate it with <m>t</m>.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <m>de = y + r*c*diff(y,t) == 0</m>
                    creates a variable <m>de</m> that contains one of the statements of the DE.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <m>des = desolve(de,[y,t],[0,1])</m>
                    invokes the Sage DE solver using our definition <m>de</m> as an argument, and:
                </li>

                <li>
                    <m>[y,t]</m>
                    identifies <m>y</m> as the function of interest and <m>t</m> as the dependent variable
                </li>
                <li>
                    <m>[0,1]</m>
                    sets the initial conditions: at <m>t = 0, y = 1</m>, or as we expressed it above, "<m>y(0) =1</m>".
                </li>
            </ul>

            <p>Now lets plot this</p>
            <sage>
                <input>
                    f(t,r,c) = des
                    plot(f(t,1,1),(t,0,5),figsize=(4,3))
                </input>
                <output>e^(-t/(c*r))</output>
            </sage>

            <p>Lets now take a more general solution.</p>
            <sage>
                <input>
                    f(t,a,b,r,c) = (a-b) * des + b
                    show(f)
                    lbl = text("$RC \, Circuit, \, r = 10000\Omega, \, c = 100\mu f $",(3,3),fontsize=12,rgbcolor='#006000')
                    p = plot(f(t,0,10,10000,100e-6),(t,0,5), figsize=(4,3),axes_labels=['time','v'])
                    show(p+lbl)
                </input>
                <output>e^(-t/(c*r))</output>
            </sage>
        </p>
    </section>

</chapter>
