<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<frontmatter xml:id="frontmatter" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <titlepage>

        <author>
            <!--<personname>John A Giannelli</personname>-->
            <department>Director</department>
            <institution>Giannelli Technology Limited</institution>
            <email>john@giannelli.co.uk</email>
        </author>

        <credit>
            <title>Sage Exercises for Anna</title>
            <author>
                <personname>Anna J Giannelli</personname>
                <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
                <institution>University of Edinburgh</institution>
            </author>
        </credit>

        <date><today /></date>

    </titlepage>


    <biography>
        <title>About John A Giannelli</title>
        <p>Freelance IT Professional currently working for BSkyB, Livingston, Scotland.</p>

        <p>He also likes to keep up with developments in modern Physic partly in an attempt to slow down brain degradation post the half century land mark!</p>
        <p>He is currently learning Sage Math and has stumbled across the fantastic lectures of Gilbert Strang and the Mathbook XML of Robert Beezer.</p>
    </biography>

    <dedication>
        <p>
            <line>To my children</line>
            <line>They are a constant reminder of what it is all about.</line>
        </p>
        <p>In Memory of Jack.</p>
    </dedication>

    <acknowledgement>

        <p>I would like to acknowledge the following people from whom I may have stolen some material. </p>

        <ul>
            <li><p>Gilbert Strang, MIT</p></li>
            <li><p>Robert Beezer, University of Puget Sound</p></li>
        </ul>

    </acknowledgement>

    <preface>

        <p>I have a degree in Physics from many years ago and have recently taken to refreshing my knowledge on it.
            First by working my way through the fine <url href="http://theoreticalminimum.com/courses">Theoretical Minimum</url>
            material by Leonard Susskind and more recently the fantastic series of Linear Algebra lectures given by Gilbert Strang at MIT.
            These lectures are hosted at
            <url href="https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/mathematics/18-06-linear-algebra-spring-2010/">MITOPENCOURSEWARE Linear Algebra</url></p>

        <p>I hope to be refreshed enough in my understanding so as to be able to get past the first chapter of
            <url href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Quantum-Field-Theory-Gifted-Amateur/dp/019969933X">Quantum Field Theory For the Gifted Amateur</url>.
            So far this is not happening very quickly!</p>

        <p>This notebook is an online repository of some Sage Math techniques I have come across in the above pursuits.
            It is at a very rudimentary level and is far from organised. Over time it may become more coherent and be useful to others. </p>

        <p>The format of this book is taken from Robert Beezer's wonderful work with <url href="http://mathbook.pugetsound.edu">MathBook XML</url>.</p>
        <p>Sage (<url href="http://sagemath.org">sagemath.org</url>) is a free, open source, software system for advanced mathematics,
            which is ideal for assisting with a study of abstract algebra.
            Sage can be used either on your own computer, a local server, or on SageMathCloud
            (<url href="https://cloud.sagemath.com">https://cloud.sagemath.com</url>). </p>

        <attribution>
            <line>John A Giannelli</line>
            <line>Linlithgow, Scotland 2016</line>
        </attribution>

    </preface>

</frontmatter>
