<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="sets" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Using Sage Math</title>


    <introduction>
        <p>
            There are several approaches to using Sage Math: using sage math online, downloading the
            source and running locally, using SageMath Cells embedded in your own web documents,
            and even installing android or iOS Apps on your phone or tablet.
        </p>
        <p>This section has notes for some of these methods.
        </p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="section-note-on-proofs">
        <title>SageMath Online</title>

        <introduction>

            <p>
                Probably the easiest way to familiarise yourself with SageMath is to use a Sage Math Cloud Server.
                From the main <url href="http://www.sagemath.org">SageMath</url> page select the
                <url href="https://cloud.sagemath.com/projects">Sage Online</url> link. You will
                have to set up an account but these are free for basic usage.
            </p>


        </introduction>

        <subsection>
            <title>Some Cautions and Suggestions</title>

            <p>There are several different strategies for proving propositions. In addition to using different methods
                of proof, students often make some common mistakes when they are first learning how to prove theorems.
                To aid students who are studying abstract mathematics for the first time, we list here some of the
                difficulties that they may encounter and some of the strategies of proof available to them. It is a good
                idea to keep referring back to this list as a reminder. (Other techniques of proof will become apparent
                throughout this chapter and the remainder of the text.)
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>A theorem cannot be proved by example; however, the standard way to show that a statement is not
                        a theorem is to provide a counterexample.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>Quantifiers are important. Words and phrases such as <em>only</em>, <em>for all</em>, <em>for
                        every</em>, and <em>for some</em> possess different meanings.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>Never assume any hypothesis that is not explicitly stated in the theorem.
                        <em>You cannot take things for granted.</em>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>Suppose you wish to show that an object <em>exists</em> and is <em>unique</em>. First show that
                        there actually is such an object. To show that it is unique, assume that there are two such
                        objects, say <m>r</m> and <m>s</m>, and then show that <m>r = s</m>.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>Sometimes it is easier to prove the contrapositive of a statement. Proving the statement
                        <q>If <m>p</m>, then
                            <m>q</m>
                        </q>
                        is exactly the same as proving the statement
                        <q>If not <m>q</m>, then not <m>p</m>.
                        </q>
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>Although it is usually better to find a direct proof of a theorem, this task can sometimes be
                        difficult. It may be easier to assume that the theorem that you are trying to prove is false,
                        and to hope that in the course of your argument you are forced to make some statement that
                        cannot possibly be true.
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>

            <p>Remember that one of the main objectives of higher mathematics is proving theorems. Theorems are tools
                that make new and productive applications of mathematics possible. We use examples to give insight into
                existing theorems and to foster intuitions as to what new theorems might be true. Applications,
                examples, and proofs are tightly interconnected<mdash/>much more so than they may seem at first
                appearance.
            </p>

        </subsection>

    </section>


    <xi:include href="./sage/sets-sage.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="./sage/sets-sage-exercises.xml"/>

</chapter>
